When we look at the marketing ecosystem,
如今的市场营销已发展地较为完整 自成一套生态体系
today's marketer has access to a staggering amount of data,
市场分析师已能获取到大量的数据
and the challenge is that you're expected to be able to capture,
现在的挑战是如何抓取到相关数据
analyze, and report on all of this data,
正确分析和汇报这些数据
and it can be overwhelming.
这个非常有挑战性
A common graphic that gets passed around in the industry is
业内广泛传播地一张图是屏幕上这张横图
this landscape diagram from Chiefmartech.com.
来自 Chiefmartech.com.
Updated in 2018, this super graphic displays
这张超级图表最新更新于 2018 年
over 6,800 different marketing technology solutions,
它囊括了超 6,800 个不同的营销技术解决方案
every new platform, tool,
包括所有的新平台、新工具、数据供应商
and data vendor contributes to a digital ecosystem that is beyond mind-boggling.
而这些平台、工具、供应商组成了整个令人惊叹的营销生态体系
Now, when we think about marketing analytics,
如何着手开始做市场分析？
we often start with the tool that we're most familiar with,
大部分肯定是选择自己最熟悉的工具
and then we look at the world of analytics through that lens.
然后通过工具来进一步分析
For many of us, that might be Google Analytics.
对大多数人来说 最常用的是 Google Analytics
It's arguably the most popular marketing analytics platform,
它是使用最广泛的市场分析平台 当然也有人持不同观点
but Google Analytics provides us one view.
但问题是 Google Analytics 只能提供一方面的数据
It's primarily looking at our website metrics.
这个平台主要用来监测网站指标
We're seeing things such as how much time people spend on our website,
比如 用户在网站停留的时间
what pages they look at,
用户浏览过的页面
and whether they buy or abandon our site.
用户是否在网站做出购买行为 或者弃用
But Google Analytics can't answer every question,
所以 Google Analytics 并不能回答所有问题
and as you saw,
但是 正如刚才的图所示
there's clearly enough data solutions out there to
对于我们可能有的每一个问题
answer just about any question we may have.
我们其实都可以找到合适的解决工具
So when it comes to analytics,
这个巨大的营销分析生态体系可以帮助我们
we have this giant ecosystem by which we can pull all of our insights out of,
获取我们所需要的任何数据洞察
but we don't necessarily need all of these tools.
但是我们也不是需要运用到每一个工具
In fact, we likely only need a fraction of them.
事实上 我们只需要一部分工具就够了
You see this entire ecosystem gives us access to specific answers based on our needs.
也就是说 这个体系能支持我们根据业务需要去找到我们要的特定答案
We can find the one tool that answers the question that we have.
总有一款工具适合我们
For example, we might use a tool to generate
比如 我们需要一个工具来根据我们网站的用户行为来
heat maps based on user behavior on our website,
生成一张热图
and then we'll capture data from that,
然后我们再根据热图观察数据
or we might be running ads on a different platform such as AdWords,
或者我们在 AdWords、Twitter、Facebook 投放广告
and there we can also capture data.
也可以获得数据
We may also use a tool to evaluate call volumes at our call center
再比如 我们需要一个工具来评估客服中心的话务量
or maybe a tool specific to measuring keyword ranking in our search results.
或者一个工具来帮我们对搜索结果进行关键词排名
Now, all of this data is native to that platform.
这个平台体系包括了以上提及的所有数据
So each platform is doing a very specific job and capturing a very specific set of data.
每个工具都有其特定的应用 以及抓取特定的数据
Now, what we can do is we can go to each tool and look at
我们需要做的是找到恰当的工具 评估其抓取的数据
that data and perhaps we can pull it down
也可以手动导出数据
manually just like we would do in Google Analytics.
就像在 Google Analytics 里一样
We could load this data up into various spreadsheets and combine it,
我们可以将这些数据导入电子表格 然后对数据进行整合
but the ecosystem also gives us access to
当然 这个生态体系里也有能对数据进行
software that automatically aggregates all of that data.
自动整合的软件
So we can plug in data from each of these tools and use
所以我们也可以从不同工具导入数据到同一个平台
one platform to look at all of that data in combination.
然后用这个平台来观测整体数据
This can make our life easier.
对于我们来说就方便了很多
So we can use this software to combine our data with
这个平台也可以帮我们整合其他人的数据
other people's data to get really rich insights on our metrics.
从而获得关于指标方面的真正有用的洞察
Like we mentioned earlier, most of that data is
我们之前提到过 大部分数据其实来源于几处而已
these sources make up part of what we call
这些来源组成了市场营销栈 (marketing technology stack)
our marketing technology stack or MarTech for short.
简称 MarTech
Now, the technology that you're going to use will
你应用到的营销分析工具都对应于
typically align to the various parts of the marketing funnel,
市场营销漏斗的某个阶段
and much about what we talked in analytics really refers back to this marketing funnel.
很多分析都跟营销漏斗有关
If you remember, the marketing funnel goes Awareness,
营销漏斗的几个层级分别是：Awareness(认知)
Interest, Desire, Action, and Advocacy.
Interest(兴趣)  Desire(渴望\决策)  Action(购买)  Advocacy（自发宣传）
So some tools cover a lot of the funnel.
有一些工具能涵盖多个阶段
Google Analytics is a great example.
Google Analytics 就是一个这样的例子
It can display data surrounding traffic arriving at the site, top of the funnel,
它可以搜集到各种数据 包括网站浏览量 即漏斗顶层数据
then engaging on the site,
用户与网站的互动
and then converting on the site there at the bottom of that funnel.
用户在网站的转化 即漏斗底部数据
Now, some tools are specific to various areas of the funnel.
很多工具也只针对漏斗的某一个阶段
With awareness, you might be capturing data out of
比如认知阶段 你可以用 Adwords、Facebook、SEMRush 等
With an interest and desire,
在兴趣和决策阶段
you might have data coming from WordPress, HubSpot, or Mailchimp.
你可以用 WordPress、HubSpot 或者 Mailchimp
For action, well, you might be leveraging Salesforce, Optimizely,
在购买阶段 你会用到 Salesforce、Optimizely 或者 Shopify
or Shopify, and then within advocacy,
在自发宣传阶段
well, you might have your own data from your CRM.
可以用到 CRM
What you use is really going to depend on what
你用的工具最终取决于你在漏斗的每一个阶段
your business goals are within each area of the funnel.
想达成什么样的业务目标
So as you can see,
综上
we have all of these sources,
我们有很多数据来源
and then we have all of these areas of
有客户旅程的各个阶段需要分析
So we're faced with two challenges.
因此 我们面临两个挑战
The first is, where should our data come from?
首先 数据从哪里来？
The second is, how do I use that data?
第二 如何使用这些数据？
Well, there is no one size fits all approach.
没有万能的解决方案
You don't really start by picking your data sources.
事实上 我们首先要做的不是选择数据来源
You actually start by picking your strategy.
而是决定我们的业务策略
So we can answer that first question of where the data comes from,
只有知道了目标是什么
by figuring out our objectives.
才能决定恰当的数据来源是什么
What does our business do?
我们的业务模型是什么？
What information helps us do it better?
什么样的市场信息有助于我们的业务开展？
Really, we're trying to figure out what happens at each stage of our customer journey,
我们真的需要去了解客户在每个阶段都会做什么
and then we need to figure out how to measure
以及如何去衡量这些客户表现
that so that we can make more informed decisions.
最终才能做出正确决策
Now, when it comes time to apply the data,
那如何应用这些数据呢？
we have to think about the action that we want to take.
我们需要想想我们希望采取什么样的行动
You see, we collect and use data to inform decisions.
数据的收集和应用最终都是服务于业务决策
So we really need to think about the question we're
所以我们需要去想想我们到底希望解决什么样的业务问题
trying to answer or the decision we want to make,
以及希望采取什么样的行动
and then work from there.
应该从这些思考出发
So as you can see, the way that you can use this ecosystem,
也就是说 运用这个生态体系有两种方式
can be figured out either top down or bottom up.
从顶层到底层 或者从底层到顶层
Either start with your objective,
从业务目标开始去定位
and then pinpoint all the data that you'll collect across
你需要在漏斗的每一个阶段收集的数据
the funnel or start with the question you want to answer,
或者 从你想解决的业务问题开始
and figure out what data you need to get that answer.
然后去思考需要哪些数据才能获得你想要的答案